(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-31T22:38:42.026798",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.7-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
ちわーす！ホロライブ2期生大空スバルでーす！
'Sup! Hololive 2nd Generation Oozora Subaru here!
ということで 1級船舶免許を取ってから なんと1年が経ちました！
So, it's actually been one whole year since I got my Class 1 boat license!
大空スバルです！今回はロケに来ております！
I'm Oozora Subaru! Today, we're out on location!
ゲストはミオしゃ〜！
Our guest is Miosha~!
はーい！ウチウチ ウチだよ 大神ミオだよー！ホロライブゲーマーズの大神ミオでーす！
Haaai! It's me, it's Mio, Ookami Mio! I'm Ookami Mio from Hololive Gamers!
今日は来てくれてありがとう！
Thanks for coming today!
いや 呼ばれたは呼ばれたけど…今日何をするんでしょうか？
Well, I came because you invited me, but... what are we doing today?
今日の企画言っちゃっていいわけ？
Can I announce today's project?
あーまあ じゃあ言っちゃってもらって…！
Ah, well, go ahead and tell me...!
では参ります！大空スバル いざ大海原へ！ミオしゃを海のドライブに連れて行くー！ということで
Here goes! Oozora Subaru sets out for the open ocean! Taking Miosha on a drive across the sea! And so...
ええー！？
Ehhh?!
大空クルーズ第1号のお客様がミオしゃに決定しましたー！
Miosha has been officially chosen as the very first passenger of Oozora Cruises!
いやいやいやいやいや…
No no no no no...
ガチで怖いから…ガチで…
I'm seriously scared... For real.
ねえ大丈夫大丈夫！ガチ免許あるから！免許！
Hey, it's okay, it's okay! I have a real license! A license!
いやいやいやいやいや…
No no no no no...
シオンと取った免許あるから大丈夫だから！
I have the license I got with Shion, so it's totally fine!
いやいやいや…免許取り立ての運転ほど怖い事ねえじゃん！
No no no... There's nothing scarier than someone driving right after getting their license!
いや しかも一回スバル…個人的にちゃんと運転しに行ってるから！
No, plus Subaru actually went out to practice driving on my own once!
あ 練習済みってこと？
Ah, so you've practiced?
そう！練習もしてきたから 任せてよ！
Yep! I practiced, so leave it to me!
学科の成績良かったから！
My written exam scores were great, too!
しかもさ ミオしゃと言えば釣りでしょ？
Besides, when you think of Miosha, you think of fishing, right?
いや そんな事ないからね！？
No, that's not true at all!
いやいや ミオしゃと言えば釣りだから 釣りしてさ 美味い魚でも食おうよ！
No way, fishing is your thing! Let's go fishing and eat some delicious fish!
おー じゃあ今日は船釣りするって事？
Ooh, so we're boat fishing today?
そう！船釣りをします！だがスバル免許取ったんですけど 船の運転は！本当に危なくて…
Yes! We'll be boat fishing! But while Subaru got her license, steering a boat is really dangerous!
やめてよ！なんか不安になるような事言うの…
Stop that! Don't say things that make me nervous...
いや マジで本当に死にたくなかったら今日見張り手伝ってほしい 本当に！
No, seriously, if you don't want to die, please help keep watch today! Seriously!
怖いよ〜！！
That's terrifying!!
船のね 事故って結構多いんだって！
I heard boating accidents happen quite often!
そうなんだ〜
Is that so~?
そう だから海に入る以上！安全についてもしっかり学ばないといけない！
Right, so as long as we're going out to sea, we need to learn proper safety!
ということで 今回はなんと！海上保安庁さんにご協力いただいております！
And so, we have the Japan Coast Guard assisting us today!
ええっ！？海上保安庁！？
Eh?! The Coast Guard?!
海の安全について色々教えてくれるみたいなので 早速行ってみよう！
They'll teach us various things about marine safety, so let's get right to it!
ということで！今回ご協力いただく秋山さんでーす！よろしくお願いします！
And so! Here is Akiyama-san, who will be helping us today! Nice to meet you!
よろしくお願いします 千葉海上保安部の秋山です 今日は一緒に！勉強していきましょう！
Nice to meet you. I'm Akiyama from the Chiba Coast Guard Office. Let's learn together today!
おおー！よろしくお願いします！
Ooh! Nice to meet you!
今日はね なんと！船の運転にあたって！色々ちょっと教えていただけると聞いたんですけど よろしくお願いします！
Today, we heard that you'll be teaching us all sorts of things about operating a boat, so we look forward to it!
海を 安全に楽しむためのポイントを クイズを交えてご紹介させていただきたいと思います！
I would like to introduce key points for enjoying the ocean safely through a quiz format!
色々教えてもらえるってことか！
So you'll be teaching us through that!
ちょっと待ってミオしゃ聞いた？クイズだって…！クイズやばいんですけど！
Wait a second, did you hear that, Miosha? A quiz...! I'm terrible at quizzes!
ちょっと待って でもウチは何も知らないよ？もしかしてスバルだけが答えるってコト？
Wait, but I don't know anything, you know? Does that mean only Subaru will be answering?
なんで！？一緒に協力しようっていう気は無いの！？お前！当事者意識！当事者意識！
Why?! Don't you feel like cooperating with me?! Take ownership! Take some ownership!
低めかもしれない…ウチ…申し訳ないけど
Mine might be pretty low... Sorry about that.
当事者意識持ってくれ！ミスれねえんだこれ…
Have some ownership! I can't mess this up...
え ミスれないの？
Eh, you can't make mistakes?
え ミスれないよ！だってスバルが！ちゃんと答えて…みなさんに伝えるって事ですよね？つまり
I can't! Because Subaru needs to answer correctly... and inform everyone watching, right? In other words.
はい そうです！
Yes, that's right!
やべえ…やべえよ…
Oh no... Oh crap...
それでは秋山さん！よろしくお願いします！
Well then, Akiyama-san, please take it away!
よろしくお願いします
Nice to meet you.
日本の領土は約38万平方キロメートルで 世界で61番目の面積となっているんですけれども
Japan's land territory is about 380,000 km², ranking 61st in the world, but...
領土を囲む領海 排他的経済水域を含めると 約447万平方キロメートル
when you include the territorial waters and Exclusive Economic Zone (EEZ) surrounding it, it spans about 4,470,000 km²,
世界で 10位以内の数字となっています
putting it within the top 10 in the world.
ヤバイじゃん！
That's insane!
いや だからさ 日本って島国じゃん！周りに海がいっぱいあるからって事ですよね？
Right, after all, Japan is an island nation! Because it's surrounded by so much sea, right?
そうです 海上保安庁はこの広大なエリアを11の管区に分けて
That's correct. The Japan Coast Guard divides this vast area into 11 regional jurisdictions,
海上保安官約1万5千人で 24時間365日守り続けています
and with about 15,000 coast guard officers, we protect it 24/7, 365 days a year.
え！凄いよ！15000人だけなんだよ？ていうか
Whoa, that's amazing! Wait, only 15,000 people?!
海上保安庁は少ない人数で頑張っているので スバルさん！
The Coast Guard works hard with a small team, so Subaru-san...
良かったら！海上保安官になりませんか！
if you'd like, would you want to become a Coast Guard officer?
ええーっ！？入っちゃおうかなー！！
Ehhh?! Maybe I'll join!!
スカウトされてる！
You're being scouted!
YAGOOバイバイ！俺 海上保安庁になる！
Bye-bye YAGOO! I'm gonna become a Coast Guard officer!
大丈夫そうかな？結構ポンコツですよ？
Would that really be okay? She's quite a klutz, you know?
ちょっと忘れ物とか結構スゴイんですけど 大丈夫ですかね？ちょっと忘れちゃうんですけど…
I tend to forget things a lot... Is that really okay? I'm pretty forgetful...
どういう人が適性があるんですか？
What kind of person is suited for it?
確かに！
True!
スバルさんのように真面目な…方が大丈夫です！
Diligent people like you, Subaru-san, are perfectly fine!
真面目なんだ！
I'm diligent!
次は 楽しいはずの海でのレジャーが悲しい事故にならないように
Next, to ensure that fun ocean leisure doesn't turn into a tragic accident,
自分の命を救うための3つの基本をご紹介します
I will introduce three basic rules for saving your own life.
まず1つ目がライフジャケットの常時着用です
First is always wearing a life jacket.
万が一 船から海に落ちてしまった場合
In the unlikely event that you fall into the sea from a boat,
ライフジャケットを着用しているだけで 着用していない人と比べると 助かる確率が4倍にもなります
simply wearing a life jacket increases your survival rate by four times compared to not wearing one.
おおー！
Ooh!
ですので 海でマリンレジャーを楽しむ際には ライフジャケットの常時着用をお願いします
Therefore, when enjoying marine leisure at sea, please make sure to always wear a life jacket.
はい！
Yes!
ただし ライフジャケットを正しく着用していても脱げてしまったり
However, even if worn, it could slip off if not worn properly,
古いものを使い続けているとうまく膨らまなかったりしますので
or if it's too old, it might not inflate properly,
正しい着用と定期的な点検を心掛けてくださいね
so please ensure proper fitting and regular inspections.
はい！分かりました！
Yes! Got it!
次は 携帯電話等の連絡手段の確保です
Next is securing communication methods like mobile phones.
皆さんは普段の生活の中でスマートフォンを持ち歩いていると思うんですけれども
I'm sure everyone usually carries their smartphone in daily life, but...
はい
Yes.
海でもこれが非常に重要となります
this is also extremely important at sea.
ほおー
Ooh.
海での事故に遭ってしまった場合 海上保安庁などの救助機関にいち早く連絡することが重要みなのですが
If you encounter an accident at sea, promptly contacting rescue agencies like the Coast Guard is vital,
スマートフォンを海に落としてしまって通報できない といったことも多いため
but people frequently drop their phones in the water and can't make emergency calls,
このようにストラップ付きの防水パック等で持ち歩くことが大切なんです
so carrying it in a waterproof case with a strap like this is essential.
おおー！なるほどね
Ooh! I see.
最後…
Lastly...
警察には110番、
Just like 110 for the police,
消防には119番といった番号と同様に
and 119 for the fire department,
海上保安庁にも緊急通報用の電話番号があるのですが、
the Japan Coast Guard also has an emergency phone number.
皆さんご存知ですか？
Do you all know what it is?
えー知らなかった！ウチは！
Eh, I didn't know that!
スバル知ってるこれ！
Subaru knows this!
1級小型免許をお持ちの スバルさんなら 当然知っていると思います。
As a holder of a First Class Small Boat license, I'm sure Subaru-san naturally knows.
やば 圧ヤバい 圧ヤバい
Oh no, the pressure is insane! The pressure is insane!
海の事件・事故は118番！
For maritime incidents and accidents, it's 118!
すごいです、正解です。
Amazing, that is correct!
よかったー！圧ヤバかったー！
Thank goodness! That pressure was real!
ここからは本格的に 何問かクイズを出題していきたいと思います。
From here on, I'd like to present a few proper quiz questions.
やばい！さっきの序章だったんだって！
Oh no! That earlier part was just the warm-up!
え！そうなの！？がっつりクイズかと思ってたら
Eh! Really?! I thought that was the actual quiz!
これから海に出るスバルさんに 海上交通のルールについて質問です！
To Subaru-san, who is heading out to sea, here is a question about maritime traffic rules!
はい！
Yes!
こちらにスバルさんが操船している船と、右側にミオさんが乗っている船があります。
Here is the boat Subaru-san is navigating, and on the right is the boat Mio-san is on.
このままではぶつかってしまう恐れがあるため、スバルさんが取るべき行動は次のうちどれでしょう？
At this rate, there is a risk of collision. Which action should Subaru-san take?
んー、ミオちゃん分かるわけ？
Hmm... Mio-chan, do you know?
この距離感だったら急げば行けるーみたいな感じになりそうじゃない？
With this distance, wouldn't you feel like, "If I hurry, I can make it!"?
ふはは！そんなわけはないのだ！
Hahaha! There's no way that's right!
なんだそのふはは
What's with that evil laugh?
これスバルね、これね、船舶免許で勉強したことある！これ知ってるよ！
Subaru studied this for the boat license! I know this!
いや、そうだよねー。
Well, you should, right?
うん。これは、4番！右に舵を切り相手を避ける、です！
Yeah. This is number 4! "Steer starboard to avoid the other vessel"!
正解は、4番です！
The correct answer is number 4!
おー！そうなんだ！
Oh! So that's how it is!
このような状況では、海上衝突予防法という法律によって、相手を右側に見る船舶が相手を避ける必要があるんです。
Under the Act on Preventing Collisions at Sea, the vessel that sees the other on its starboard side must give way.
へぇ〜。
I see~.
この場合はスバルさんの船が右に舵を切って避けるか、減速または停止してミオさんの船を避けるのが正解になります。
In this case, Subaru-san's boat steering right, or slowing down/stopping to avoid Mio-san's boat, is correct.
スバルこういう時もう怖いから止まっちゃいます！先に行ってください！
In times like that, Subaru would get scared and just stop! "Please go ahead!"
あー！でも止まってもいいってことですもんね。
Ah! But stopping is totally fine too, right?
そうです。
That's correct.
次の問題！
[Next Question!]
ここに架空の湾、スバル湾があります。
Here is a fictional bay called Subaru Bay.
スバル湾。
Subaru Bay.
船が入港するためにスバル航路を通って入港します。
To enter the port, ships pass through the Subaru Fairway.
航路のここに設置される航路標識の組み合わせをこの中からお答えください。
From these options, please choose the correct fairway mark combination to place here.
船舶免許持ってるので分かります！
I have a boat license, so I know this!
おー！
Ooh!
これは右舷標識と左舷標識なので、
These are starboard and port lateral marks, so...
赤い三角形の方が右で、
the red triangular one goes on the right,
緑の四角の方が左側に入ります。
and the green square one goes on the left side.
で、上も一緒のように入ります。
And the ones further ahead are placed the same way.
へぇ〜。
I see~.
スバルさん、流石です。
Subaru-san, impressive as expected!
よっしゃー！
All right!
あぶねー。ちゃんと分かってた！
Phew! You really knew it!
当たり前じゃん！
Of course I do!
では、次の問題です。
Now, on to the next question.
次の問題！
[Next Question!]
ここに航路標識を設置して船に対して標識の西側は安全に走れますよということを示したいのですが、
We want to place a mark here to indicate that safe navigable water lies to the west of it.
その場合、この4つのうちのどれを設置すればいいと思いますか？
In that case, which of these four marks should be installed?
ヤバいよミオちゃん…これはちょっと難しいよ。
Oh no, Mio-chan... This is pretty tough.
ウチは全然さっぱり！0%分かりませんけど！
I don't have a single clue! I understand 0% of this!
え、でもたぶん、一番右のやつだった気がします！
Uh, but I think it was probably the one on the far right!
え、その心は？
Eh, what's your reasoning?
その心は、なんか一番右に置いてあるやつが西なんだよ。
My reasoning is, the one placed on the far right represents West.
へぇ〜。
I see~.
で、上上ってなってるやつが北で、下下が南で、
The double upward triangles are North, double downward are South,
こう、なんかダイヤマークになってるやつが東なんじゃなかったかなぁ。
and wasn't the diamond-shaped one East?
なるほど、方角を表してるってこと？
I see, so they indicate cardinal directions?
そう！だからたぶん一番右！
Yes! So probably the one on the far right!
スバルさん、正解です。
Subaru-san, that is correct.
危ない！危ない！
That was close! So close!
ちゃんと分かってるやん。
You really do know it!
もう海上保安庁さんで間違えたら免許剥奪されちまう！
If I got it wrong in front of the Coast Guard, they'd revoke my license!
そんなの？
Really?
この航路標識は「方位標識」と呼ばれるもので、それぞれの標識の東西南北側に安全に走れる場所があるということを示しています。
These marks are called "cardinal marks," indicating where it is safe to navigate around the mark.
おー！
Ooh!
本格的なクイズで海難防止について勉強してきましたが、船の事故についてもご紹介させてください！
We studied maritime safety through quizzes, but please let me share some facts on boat accidents too!
うん。
Yeah.
令和7年に海上保安庁が取り扱った船の事故は1,711隻であり、そのうち、約半数の833隻がプレジャーボートでの事故となっています。
In 2025, the Coast Guard handled 1,711 boat accidents, with roughly half (833) being pleasure boats.
プレジャーボートって何？
What is a pleasure boat?
なんかスバルの乗れる、すごいみんなで遊んだりとかするやつ！
The kind Subaru can pilot, like boats people use to hang out and have fun together!
あー！釣りしたりとか、観光用の船みたいな？
Ah! Like boats for fishing or sightseeing?
そう！
Exactly!
この事故のうち約7割が船の整備不良や見張り不十分といった「人的要因」と呼ばれる事故となっているんです。
About 70% of these accidents are due to "human factors," such as poor maintenance or improper lookout.
プレジャーボートを操船する方は、発航前点検、適切な見張りの実施を行い、事故を未然に防ぎましょう。
For those navigating pleasure boats, perform pre-departure checks and maintain proper watch to prevent accidents.
はい！
Yes!
発航前点検の実施は、プレジャーボートの事故では機関故障が多くを占めているんです。
As for pre-departure checks, engine breakdowns make up a large portion of pleasure boat accidents.
船が動かなくなったことによって流されて浅瀬に乗り上げてしまったり、他の船にぶつかって二次災害に繋がることもあることから、
Losing power can cause a boat to drift and run aground or collide with other vessels, causing secondary disasters.
発航前点検は必ず実施して船を適切に管理しましょう。
Always conduct pre-departure checks to properly maintain your boat.
はい！
Yes!
そして、見張りの実施が安全運行の基本です。
And maintaining a proper lookout is fundamental to safe navigation.
海は広く、他の船とぶつかってしまう恐れはないと思われがちなんですけれども、見張り不十分による船同士の衝突は多く発生しているんです。
People often assume the sea is vast so collisions won't occur, but many happen due to improper lookout.
船長だけではなく、ミオさんのように船に乗っている人たちにも常に見張りを行って、事故を防いでください。
Not just the captain, but passengers like Mio-san on board should also constantly keep watch to prevent accidents.
ウチも見とかなきゃいけないってコト？
Does that mean I have to keep watch too?
当たり前じゃん！〇にたくなかったら見張りしてないとさ！
Of course! If you don't wanna die, you gotta keep watch!
こえぇ...
Scary...
見張りは本当に大事ってめちゃめちゃ言われたから！
They emphasized over and over how important keeping watch is!
え、めっちゃ大事ですよね？
Like, it's super important, right?
はい、とても大切です。
Yes, it is very important.
見張りの基本は、全方位にわたり、対象物を特定せず、継続的に繰り返して行うことが重要です。
The basis of watchkeeping is to continuously and repeatedly monitor all directions without fixing on a single object.
うーん...
Hmm...
じゃあウチも見張り…頑張ります！
Then I'll do my best at keeping watch too!
頑張ってね！
Good luck!
という事で！今回ご協力いただいた、海上保安庁の秋山さん！本当にありがとうございました！
And so! Akiyama-san from the Japan Coast Guard who assisted us today, thank you so much!
ありがとうございました！
Thank you very much!
ありがとうございました！いっぱい釣れるといいですね！行ってらっしゃい！
Thank you very much! I hope you catch a lot! Have a safe trip!
行ってきます！
We're off!
いっぱい釣るぞ！ / 釣るぞ！釣るぞー！
Let's catch a ton! / Let's do it!
ということで、乗船しましたー！
And so, we've boarded the boat!
え、こ、これがスバルの船…？
Wait, th-this is Subaru's boat...?
そう、これがスバルの船らしいです。なんか結構デカくてビビってます！
Yeah, apparently this is my boat. It's pretty big, so I'm kind of terrified!
いや、デカくてビビってるってことはこれレンタルだよね？多分。
If you're terrified because it's big, that means it's a rental, right? Probably.
いや、そうだよ。これレンタルさせていただきました。
Yeah, that's right. We're renting this one.
今回はですね、セントラルさんの東京湾フィッシングに参加します。
Today, we're taking part in Central's Tokyo Bay Fishing plan.
木更津沖から気軽に楽しめるフィッシングプランで、
It's a casual fishing plan off the coast of Kisarazu,
なんとね、ベテランスタッフさんのサポートを受けながらボートフィッシングが楽しめるということで、
where you can enjoy boat fishing while receiving support from veteran staff,
それは安心だね！
That's reassuring!
ところがどっこい！普段はですね、スタッフさんが操縦するんですけど、
However! Usually the staff steers the boat, but...
今回は許可をいただいたので、スバルが運転します！
since we got permission today, Subaru is driving!
えぇぇ！？
Ehhh?!
え、ええ、それはでもあの…つ、釣りを…釣りをするってことだよね？
Uh, wait, but... we're still going fishing, right?
そうだよ、今日は釣りをしますよ。
Yeah, we're fishing today.
なんかポイントとか分かってるわけ？
Do you even know where the fishing spots are?
分かんない！だからね、スタッフさんに教えてもらおうと思う。
No idea! So I'm gonna have the staff guide us.
なるほどね！
I see!
ちなみに今回はね、シロギスっていうのを釣るらしい。釣ったことある？
By the way, apparently we're fishing for Japanese whiting today. Ever caught one?
ない！
Nope!
入れ食いらしい！
They say they're biting like crazy!
入れ食い！？
Biting like crazy?!
信じてるぞ！
I'm trusting them!
本当かなぁそれ！ / 信じてるぞ、セントラルさん！
I wonder if that's true! / I believe in you, Central!
ま、行ってみましょうよ！ / はい！
Well, let's go find out! / Okay!
はい、ということで、出発準備OK！ミオしゃ、準備はいいか？
Alright, preparations to depart are complete! Miosha, are you ready?
いつでも行くぞ！
Ready whenever!
それじゃあ、大空スバル号、出航！
Then, the Oozora Subaru ship, setting sail!
出航！ / 行くぞ！
Setting sail! / Let's go!
いけるのか？本当に…
Can she really pull this off...?
まずゆっくり発進。
First, start moving slowly.
やべえ、軽い！
Oh crap, it's so light!
軽い…？
Light...?
8, 9, 10...
やべえめっちゃ軽い！ちょっと待って！
Oh crap, it's super light! Wait a second!
大丈夫だから！あーーー！大丈夫だから！
You're fine! Aaaah! You're fine!
このままだと…前方の船に突っ込みそうな感じだけど大丈夫？
At this rate... it looks like we might crash into that boat ahead, are we okay?
左から回っていきます。
I'll go around it from the left.
そうですね。おおー。
Good idea. Ooh...
やべえ、めっちゃ軽い。
Oh man, it's so light.
軽いとなにか問題が？ / ゆっくり…
Is it being light a problem? / Slowly...
軽いとー、ギュウウウンって加速する！
When it's light, it accelerates with a sudden zoom!
あ、なるほどね！うわー！あー！何この揺れ！
Ah, I see! Whoa! Ahh! What's with this rocking?!
やべえ、すぐ30出るやん！ / うわあ！
Holy crap, it hits 30 in no time! / Whoa!
すごい！めっちゃ曲がる！
Whoa! It turns so sharply!
操縦しやすいってこと？
You mean it's easy to steer?
ちょっと慣れないかも！ちょっと慣れていく。
I might not be used to it! Gonna ease into it.
右に船ある。やべえ。一旦ゆっくり。
There's a boat to the right. Crap. Slowing down for a moment.
〇にたくなかったら見張ってくれ！ / やばい、捕まるぞ！捕まるぞ！
Keep watch if you don't wanna die! / Oh crap, hold on tight!
なんか前方に、なんかでかいの浮いてる。
There's something big floating ahead.
でかいの浮いてる？
Something big floating?
うん、なんか浮いてる。
Yeah, something's floating.
何あれ？
What is that?
前のさ、船がいるじゃん。 / はい。
See that boat ahead? / Yeah.
あの船がさ、同じ方向に行こうとしてるんだけどさ、
That boat is heading in the same direction, but...
確かにね。
True.
船の後ろも行っちゃダメだからさ、追い抜いた方がいいんだけど、
you shouldn't go behind another boat, so I should overtake it, but...
スバルにそんな度胸はない！
Subaru doesn't have the guts for that!
うわあ！すげえ曲がる！ / 舵持っていかれる！めっちゃ持っていかれてるよ！
Whoa! It turns so hard! / The wheel's pulling! It's pulling you so hard!
海運転ムズイ！
Driving on the sea is hard!
持っていかれる？
Is it pulling you?
よく分かんない方に曲がる。
It turns in weird directions.
潮の流れとかがあるのかな…？
Maybe it's the tidal current...?
でも確かに、スバル今までこんなに波立ってるとこで、こんなデカイの運転した事ないかも。
True, I've probably never piloted such a big boat in water this choppy.
意外と波は立ってるんですか？船長。
Are the waves surprisingly choppy, Captain?
ま、体感だいぶ立ってますね、これ。
Well, it feels pretty choppy to me.
あ、そうなんだ。
Ah, is that so?
どうよ、スバル船長の運転は。
So, how's Captain Subaru's driving?
まだ不安はあるけど…まあ、この調子であれば、事故りはしなさそう。
I'm still a bit anxious, but... at this rate, seems like we won't crash.
スバルビビリだからな！もうやばいってなったらエンジン止めるから。
Subaru's a scaredy-cat, after all! If things get bad, I'll just kill the engine.
エンジン切っちゃうんだ。
You'll just cut the engine?
うん。もう「避けてください」のスタンスで行くから。
Yeah. I'll just go with the "Please avoid me" stance.
なるほどね。
I see.
多分スピード出した方が揺れ少ない気がする。
I feel like going faster actually causes less rocking.
いや、それはそう！それはそうなんだけどさ！
Well, that's true! That's true, but...
あの船を抜かすまでは…何があるか分からん！
until we pass that boat... you never know what could happen!
いやそうね、あの船ちょっと怖いね。
Yeah true, that boat is a bit scary.
いや、この間通る系苦手なんだよ、マジで。
Man, I'm really bad at passing between things, seriously.
心理ストレスがやばい！
The mental stress is insane!
え、なんかあの船、あそこ曲がろうとしている気がする。
Wait, I think that boat is trying to turn over there.
確かに右側にちょっとずつ… / そうだよね。
True, little by little to the right... / Right?
どうですか？初海…ライド。怖い？ / こええ
How is it? Your first time riding on the sea. Scary? / Scary.
てか、こんなにいっぱい船がいる所知らない。俺今まで… / そうなの？
I mean, I've never seen so many boats around. Up until now, I... / Really?
家の庭でずっと走ってたんや。
was basically just driving around in my own backyard.
じゃあ結構緊張感あるね！
Then this must be pretty nerve-wracking!
緊張感あるよ！
It really is!
ミオちゃん、あれ！ / うん。
Mio-chan, look at that! / Yeah.
あれ、さっき習ったやつ！
That's what we learned about earlier!
あー、あれブイ？ / ブイ！ブイ！
Ah, is that a buoy? / Buoy! A buoy!
あれよ、海上保安庁さんが付けてくれてるんや。ほんまありがとう。
That's what the Coast Guard set up for us. Seriously, thank you.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
うわー海に出る！うわーー！
Whoa, we're heading out to sea! Whoaa!
やべえ、ガチで海じゃん！
Holy crap, this is literally the open ocean!
ちょっと待って、やばすぎ！
Wait a second, this is insane!
海だー！ / 海だー！
It's the sea! / It's the ocean!
こんだけ広かったら安心感あるんじゃない？
With it being this open, doesn't it feel safer?
あるある！
Totally, totally!
初めてこんなレーダーみたいの見たわ。
First time seeing something like this radar.
おーー。
Ooh...
あの辺じゃね？
Isn't it around there?
お、この辺だ！
Oh, it's right around here!
もういいのかな？始めて。
Can we start now?
始めちゃおう！行くぞ！
Let's get started! Here we go!
フィッシュ！ / ひょーー！
Fish on! / Wheee!
それで底に着くのを待つ。
And now, we wait for it to hit the bottom.
着いたかも！ / 着いたかな？
It might have hit bottom! / Did it hit?
あ、着いた！「トン」って感じした！
Ah, it hit! I felt a "thud"!
あとはズルズルと引きずる。
Now you slowly drag it along.
するとシロギスというのが釣れるらしい
Apparently, that lets you catch Japanese whiting.
本当かなぁ？
Really?
なんか突かれてる感覚あるよ！
I feel like something's pecking at it!
本当？
Really?
なんかツンツンされてる
It feels like it's poking at it.
餌だけ食われてねぇかな？
I wonder if it just ate the bait.
どうなんだろうね
I wonder.
シロギスって頭いいのかな？
Are Japanese whiting smart, I wonder?
食い逃げされてたらどうしよう
What if it ate and ran?
でもちっちゃいから脳みそちっちゃいんじゃないの？
But since they're tiny, wouldn't their brains be tiny too?
ミオしゃ刺すね〜！
Miosha, that's savage!
ちなみにアジ釣りに行った時はさ
By the way, when I went horse mackerel fishing,
うん
Yeah.
波と同化しろって言われてよ
they told me to "become one with the waves."
海と一体化したら釣れた！
And when I really became one with the sea, I caught one!
じゃあ今日も波と一体化しなよ！早く！
Then merge with the waves today too! Hurry!
分かってるよそんなのー！
I know that already!
お、来たかも！
Oh, I might have got one!
わー！ミオちゃん、ググって引いてる
Whoa! Mio-chan, it's tugging!
来たか？来たか？え？
Did it? Did it? Eh?
来てんじゃない？引いてるよ！
Isn't it on? It's pulling!
来てないわ〜
It's not on~
来てなかった
It wasn't.
スバルも一回確認してみよ！
Let me check mine once too!
なんか赤い紐ついてる
There's some red string attached.
え？うわ！
Eh? Whoa!
来てる！来てる！
It's on! It's on!
来た来た来た来た来た！釣れてる釣れてる！
It came, it came! I caught it, I caught it!
釣れてるよ！わー！
You caught it! Whoa!
うわー！釣れたよ！
Whoa! I caught one!
釣れてる〜！
You did~!
ミオちゃん釣れるぞここ！
Mio-chan, you can catch them here!
本当に？
Really?
やっぱり海と一体化する事なんや！
You really do have to become one with the ocean!
今一体化してた…？
Were you one with the ocean just now...?
してたしてた！
I was, I was!
やべぇ釣り好きだな ホロライブ釣り部結成しようかな勝手に
Man, I love fishing. Maybe I should start the Hololive Fishing Club.
釣り部
Fishing club.
これ砂の、砂の感じがクンクン来てるのか…
I wonder if this is the feel of the sand tugging at it...
いや私もさこれ砂かなーとか思って分かんねーなと思ってた
Yeah, I was also wondering, "Is this sand?" and couldn't tell.
あ、来たかも！
Oh, I might have got one!
お、来てんじゃない？
Oh, isn't it on?
なんかグイッてなった気がする
I feel like it gave a sharp tug.
お、来てるって！ミオちゃん頑張れ！
Oh, it's definitely on! Mio-chan, go for it!
マジっすか？
Seriously?
マジっすか？本当に？でもなんか軽くなったかも
Seriously? Really? But it might have gotten lighter.
あ、来てる！
Ah, it's on!
来てる来てる来てる！やったー！
It's on, it's on, it's on! Yay!
やったー！やったー！
Yay! Yay!
ほら海と一体化するのが大事なんだって！
See! Becoming one with the sea is what matters!
取れたー！
I caught it~!
ミオちゃんもう一匹釣ろうぜ！
Mio-chan, let's catch another one!
うん、頑張りたいね
Yeah, let's do it.
どうしよう釣りの案件来ちゃったら
What if we get a fishing sponsorship?
釣りの案件…
A fishing sponsorship...
え、やべぇ来てるかも
Wait, oh man, I might have a bite.
来てる？
A bite?
来てるかこれ？逃げられちゃったかな…？
Is it on? Did it get away...?
でもなんか引いてる…？
Ah, but is it pulling...?
上げてみないと意外と分かんなかったり…
You kinda don't know until you reel it in...
でしょ？私も途中まで…
Right? Me too, halfway through...
あ、2匹釣れてる！2匹！
Ah! You caught two! Two!
え、嘘でしょ！？2匹釣れてる！？
Wait, no way?! Two of them?!
2匹ついてる！2匹ついてます！
There are two on it! Two attached!
上げて上げて上げて上げて！甲板上げて！
Bring it up, bring it up! Bring it onto the deck!
釣れてるような釣れてないようなとか言ってたら2匹釣れてたw
While saying "It feels like it's on, or maybe not," I had two!
美味そう！
Looks delicious!
え、やべぇ釣れてるかも
Wait, oh man, I might have caught one.
やべぇ入れ食いや！釣れてる！
Oh man, they're biting like crazy! It's on!
ほら！釣れてる！
Look, it's on!
あ、本当だ！釣れてる！すごい！
Ah, really! You caught one! Amazing!
来てる気がする…！
I feel like I've got one...!
どうだ？どうだ？
How is it? How is it?
来てない…
Nothing...
あ〜惜しい
Ah, so close.
魚って意外に殺意感じ取るらしい
Apparently fish can surprisingly sense killing intent.
じゃあウチは殺意が強い…ってこと！？
So that means... my killing intent is strong?!
確かに「絶対に釣ってやる…！」っていう
Indeed, like "I'm definitely gonna catch you...!"
なるほどね
I see.
ミオちゃん今何考えてるの？
Mio-chan, what are you thinking about right now?
え？今？
Eh? Right now?
うん
Yeah.
釣りって…なんか無だなって
Fishing... kinda feels like nothingness.
いやそうだよ！これ無になりにみんな来てんだもんw
No, exactly! That's why everyone comes here, to zone out!
そうなの？
Is that so?
海見てボーッとするついでに魚釣ってんだよこれ
You stare blankly at the sea, and catching fish is just on the side.
そうなんだ
I see.
デジタルデトックスにはうってつけやね
It's perfect for a digital detox, isn't it?
でしょ？
Right?
波のリズムに身を任せる
Surrendering yourself to the rhythm of the waves.
そうだ、波のリズムに身を任せ…
Right, surrender to the rhythm of the waves...
来た！
It's here!
来たー！
来てる来てる！絶対来てると思う！
It's on, it's on! I definitely think it's on!
これは多分…どうだ？
This is probably... how is it?
来てる来てる来てる！
It's on, it's on, it's on!
来た来た！やっぱり来た！
It came, it came! I knew it!
やったー！やったー！
Yay! Yay!
ミオちゃん2匹目！
Mio-chan, your second fish!
今の気持ちをどうぞ！
Tell us how you feel right now!
嬉しいです！
I'm so happy!
やったー！
Yay!
ピチピチです！
It's flopping around!
もう一回ぐらいエントリーしたら帰るか
Shall we head back after one more cast?
早ぇ！w
So soon?!
どう？ミオちゃん体力的に
How are you feeling stamina-wise, Mio-chan?
全然大丈夫だけど！
No, I'm totally fine!
本当？
Really?
走ってる時よりラクだわ
It's way easier than when we were running.
ふざけんなよそんなのw
Don't say that!
スバルの大空クルーズが良くないみたいじゃないか！
You're making it sound like Subaru's Oozora Cruise isn't good!
今日は釣った魚食べられるから！
We can eat the fish we caught today!
キスってさどういう種類の食べ方思い浮かぶ？
What ways to eat whiting come to mind?
天ぷらじゃない？
Tempura, right?
やっぱ天ぷらかなー
Tempura after all, I guess.
お刺身もいけるんだって！
Apparently you can eat it as sashimi too!
でっかいからってこと？
Because they're big?
ミオちゃん次のさ大空クルーズの生贄選んで？
Mio-chan, pick the next sacrifice for Oozora Cruise!
船酔いしなさそうで楽しんでくれそうな人がいい？
Someone who won't get seasick and would enjoy it?
うん！
Yeah!
千速とかは？
How about Chihaya?
お、千速いいじゃん！
Oh, Chihaya sounds good!
うん
Yeah.
ちは絶対楽しんでくれるでしょ！
Chiha would definitely enjoy it!
絶対楽しんでくれそうなタイプ
She's definitely the type to enjoy it.
じゃあちはに一言！
Then give a message to Chiha!
意外と酔うから絶対に酔い止めは飲んできた方がいいよ
You get surprisingly seasick, so definitely take motion sickness medicine beforehand!
千速バイク乗ってる…バイクだっけ？車だっけ？
Chihaya rides a bike... Was it a bike? Or a car?
車！
A car!
酔わないんじゃないの？意外に
Won't she surprisingly not get sick then?
どうかな〜？
Who knows~?
ちは！来年乗ってくれよな！今年でも可！
Chiha! Ride with us next year! This year works too!
でもノリノリで来てくれそう
She'd probably come with great enthusiasm.
鬼ノリいいからな！
She's super enthusiastic, after all!
莉々華とかも良さそう！
Ririka would be good too!
莉々華はさ〜何が起きるか分かんねぇからw
With Ririka, you never know what's gonna happen!
莉々華と行くんだったらスゲェの釣行きたいな
If I go with Ririka, I wanna fish for something crazy.
あ〜なるほどね
Ah~ I see.
でもフブキもめっちゃ釣り好きだからさ
Though Fubuki also loves fishing a ton.
そうなの！？
Really?!
だって事あるごとにゲーム内で釣りばっかしてるじゃん
Yeah! At every opportunity, she's always fishing in games.
あれゲームだからとかじゃなくて？
Isn't that just because it's a game?
違うよ〜！
No way~!
釣りガチャ要素強いしな！
Though fishing does have strong gacha elements!
うん
Yeah.
今日めっちゃ晴れて良かったね！
I'm glad it turned out so sunny today!
ねー！すごいよ、こんなにバチバチに晴れて
Yeah! It's amazing how completely sunny it is.
せーの！
Ready, set, go!
お、釣れてんじゃない？
Oh, didn't you catch something?
どうだどうだ？どうだ？重い気がする
How is it? How is it? I think it feels heavy!
ミオちゃんデカいの来てるんじゃないの？
Mio-chan, isn't a big one on the line?
どうだどうだ？釣れたか？
How is it? Did I catch it?
釣れた！ / やったー！
I caught it! / Yay!
うわーー！
Woahh!
おー！見事なしろぎす！
Oh, a magnificent whiting!
元気いっぱいだー
It's full of energy!
うわ、クラゲだ！すごい、浮いてる！
Whoa, a jellyfish! Amazing, it's floating!
本当だ！
You're right!
最近スバル、クラゲ食うのにハマってるから
Lately I've been hooked on eating jellyfish...
そうなの？持って帰る？
Really? Want to take it home?
いや要らない…怖いやん！
No, I don't... It's scary!
刺されると痛てぇ
It hurts if you get stung!
やべえ、これ釣れてる多分
Oh shoot, I think I caught one.
来てるか？
Is one coming?
引いてる引いてる！これは絶対釣れてる！
It's pulling, it's pulling! There's definitely one on!
おらー！
Here it comes!
キター！
It's here!
来てるー！
It's coming!
やったー！
Yay!
ミオちゃん、俺がエントリーしたい！
Mio-chan, I want to cast!
いいよ
Sure.
行くよ。いち！
Here I go. One!
にの！
Two...
さん！
...three!
おせぇ…
Too late...
「いいよ」言うの忘れてたなって今
I just realized I forgot to say "Go!"
果たして釣れるのか？
Will we catch anything?
はい、「ちょん」としました！
Okay, I gave it a little tap!
あとはミオちゃん頑張って
Now give it your best, Mio-chan!
「ちょん」ってするの分かるんだ！
Oh, you can tell when it taps!
うん
Yeah.
お、引いてる？引いてる？え、嘘？
Oh, is it pulling? Pulling? Wait, really?
お、本当だ！引いてる、引いてる！引いてる、引いてる、引いてる！
Oh, you're right! It's pulling, pulling! Pulling, pulling!
引いてる引いてる！ / なんか引いてるかも！
It's pulling! / Something might be on!
ゆっくり、ゆっくり、ゆっくり、なんか引いてるかも！
Slowly, slowly, slowly... Something might be on!
頑張れ！
You got this!
よいしょ！
Up we go!
いるいるいる！うわーー！
It's there, it's there! Whoa!
キター！
It's here!
ラストフィッシング！
Last fishing!
ラストフィッシングや！
The last fishing!
やったーー！
Yay!
という事で！
And so!
本日釣れた釣果がこちら！
Here is today's total catch!
わーー！
Woah!
ねぇ、すごいよミオちゃん、マジ！
Hey, that's amazing, Mio-chan, seriously!
わー、いっぱい釣れたねー！
Wow, we caught a ton!
14匹釣れてんだよ！ヤバ！
We caught 14 of them! Crazy!
イエイ、イエイ、イエイ！
Yay, yay, yay!
という事でミオちゃん！釣ったやつ、すぐ食べたいと思わないか？
So, Mio-chan! Don't you want to eat what we caught right away?
お〜！た、食べれるんですか？生は無理だよウチ？
Oh! C-Can we eat them? I can't do raw, you know?
いやいや、「生で行け」とは言ってないよ別に！
No, no, I didn't say to eat them raw!
このままはちょっと踊り食いはね…！狼と言えど！
Eating them alive as is would be a bit... Even for a wolf!
言ってへん！
I never said that!
これからね、これを料理して食べたいと思います！
Now, we're going to cook these and eat them!
おー、楽しみー！
Oh, can't wait!
という事で！さっき釣った魚がこちらでーす！
And so! Here are the fish we caught earlier!
えー！すごーい！もう面影ない！
Whoa! Amazing! There's no trace of how they looked!
いや、そうだよもう！
Well, yeah, obviously!
完全にない！
Completely gone!
という事でね！釣った後はやっぱ釣りたての魚を食べるのが醍醐味！
So! Eating freshly caught fish right after catching them is the best part!
うわー、贅沢！
Wow, what a luxury!
食べようぜ〜！
Let's dig in!
はーい！
Okay!
せーの！いただきます！
Ready, set... Bon appétit!
何から食べる？
What should we eat first?
え、お刺身でしょ、やっぱ！
Well, sashimi, obviously!
お刺身にできるぐらいのデカいやつって珍しいらしいよ！
Apparently, ones big enough to make sashimi out of are pretty rare!
そうなのー！？
Really?!
いただきまーす / いただきます
Bon appétit! / Let's eat.
うわー、すごい！ / すごーい！
Whoa, amazing! / Amazing!
ミオちゃんが釣ったやつだよ、それ！
That's the one you caught, Mio-chan!
本当…？適当パチこいてんだろ！
Really...? You're just making that up!
いやいや、そんな なんでそんな事言うの！
No, no, why would you say that?!
ミオちゃんが釣ったやつかもしれないじゃん！
It could really be the one you caught!
いや、分かんないだろ！
No way to tell!
いただきまーす！
Bon appétit!
美味しい！
It's delicious!
んー！歯応えがある！
Mm! It has a nice bite to it!
甘い！甘ーい！
It's sweet! So sweet!
結構噛み応えがしっかりしてて、甘いね！
It's got a really nice firm chew, and it's sweet!
見て！プリプリ！
Look! It's so plump!
凄い！肉厚だ、結構！
Wow! It's pretty thick!
普通のお刺身ではないよね
It's definitely not like ordinary sashimi.
ないでしょ！そうなんだよ！釣りたてのお刺身美味しいんだよ！
Right?! Exactly! Freshly caught sashimi is so good!
釣りたてってなんかやっぱ違うよねー
Freshly caught really does hit different.
うん。天ぷらも食べよう！
Yeah. Let's eat the tempura too!
うん！天ぷら天ぷら！いただきまーす
Yeah! Tempura, tempura! Let's eat!
うーん！うまっ！うわー！
Mmm! Delicious! Whoa!
これは美味い！
This is delicious!
でしょ！でしょってスバルが作ったわけじゃないんですけど
Right? Though it's not like I made it myself.
作っていただいたんですけど
They made it for us, though.
最高です！
It's the best!
ミオちゃんどうだった？
What did you think, Mio-chan?
大空クルーズ星3って言ってたやん
You gave Oozora Cruise 3 stars earlier, right?
なんと今ならこのプロの人が作ったご飯付き！
But now it comes with a meal cooked by professionals!
そんなん、★5になるに決まってるやん！
With that, it's definitely getting 5 stars!
イエーイ！
Yay!
それではこのご飯を食べながら、最後は「さよなら」したいと思いますけど
So while we eat this meal, we'd like to say our goodbyes...
お、もう「さよなら」のお時間なんですか？
Oh, is it already time to say goodbye?
そうだよ！今日は海上保安庁さん行ってさー
That's right! Today we visited the Coast Guard...
いや、そうだよ朝から！
Yeah, right from the morning!
そうだよ！庁舎行ってさ、ルール教えてもらってさー
Exactly! We went to their station and learned the rules...
大空クルーズが出航してさ、釣りしてさ、これ作ってもらってさー
Oozora Cruise set sail, we fished, and had this made for us...
ちょっと聞いてる？食べてるけど
Are you even listening? You're just eating!
それじゃあ！大空クルーズ！
And so! Oozora Cruise...
これにて！第一部、終！
With this, Part 1 concludes!
じゃあみんな！またねー！
See you all later!
ばいば〜い！
Bye-bye!
またのご来店…じゃないわ。ご来場？ / なんて言うの？
Thank you for dining... wait, no. Visiting? / What do you say?
ご…ご…船に乗れー！バイバーイ！
G-Get on the boat! Bye-bye!
バイバーイ！
Bye-bye!
次はお前だ！！
You're next!!